<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Causality | Qingzhou Zhang</title>
    <link>https://zqzneptune.github.io/tags/causality/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://zqzneptune.github.io/tags/causality/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Causality</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>©2014-2025 Qingzhou Zhang (CC) BY-NC-SA 4.0. All thoughts and opinions here are my own.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://zqzneptune.github.io/images/icon_huf504e8a2f7c5cf9e43cec507892894a0_49847_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Causality</title>
      <link>https://zqzneptune.github.io/tags/causality/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>From What to Why: How Perturb-seq Rewrote the Rules of Functional Genomics</title>
      <link>https://zqzneptune.github.io/post/2021-02-03_perturbseqinit/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zqzneptune.github.io/post/2021-02-03_perturbseqinit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-core-finding-in-a-nutshell&#34;&gt;The Core Finding in a Nutshell&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m taking a look back at the foundational 2016 paper from the Regev and Friedman labs that introduced Perturb-seq. At its core, they developed a method that welds a pooled CRISPR screen to single-cell RNA sequencing. For the first time, this allowed them to systematically knock out genes and read out the full downstream transcriptional consequences in thousands of individual cells at once, in a single experiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-problem-a-chasm-between-scale-and-depth&#34;&gt;The Problem: A Chasm Between Scale and Depth&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before this work, functional genomics was a frustrating trade-off. We could either go big with pooled screens that measured simple, one-dimensional outputs like cell survival, or go deep with low-throughput, one-gene-at-a-time transcriptomics. There was simply no way to causally link hundreds of genetic perturbations to high-dimensional phenotypes at scale. How do you build a causal map of a cell&amp;rsquo;s regulatory network if you can only see one intersection at a time? This paper provided the first practical roadmap to bridge that chasm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;their-analytical-engine-a-linear-model-with-biological-awareness&#34;&gt;Their Analytical Engine: A Linear Model with Biological Awareness&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The elegance of Perturb-seq isn&amp;rsquo;t just in the wet lab design. Computationally, they built a framework called MIMOSCA (Multi-Input-Multi-Output-Single-Cell-Analysis). At its heart, it&amp;rsquo;s a regularized linear model that attributes changes in each gene&amp;rsquo;s expression to the presence of a specific sgRNA. The real genius, however, is how they layered in covariates. The model doesn&amp;rsquo;t just capture the perturbation&amp;rsquo;s effect; it systematically models and subtracts the confounding effects of technical noise (like sequencing depth per cell) and, most importantly, pre-existing biological heterogeneity (like cell cycle or differentiation state). This layered approach allows them to isolate the true, direct impact of the gene knockout from other sources of variation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-result-that-demands-attention&#34;&gt;The Result That Demands Attention&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most profound insight for me was their ability to disentangle direct transcriptional regulation from shifts in cell state proportions. When they first modeled the data from dendritic cells, the inferred regulatory network was a bit blurry (Fig 3A). The &amp;lsquo;aha!&amp;rsquo; moment came after they accounted for cell state. They realized that a transcription factor knockout might not create an entirely &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; cellular program, but rather push cells from, say, a &amp;ldquo;pro-inflammatory&amp;rdquo; state to an &amp;ldquo;antiviral&amp;rdquo; state—both of which already exist in the unperturbed population. After computationally correcting for this cell state shifting, the direct regulatory links became razor-sharp (Fig 3E). This is a fundamental lesson: a perturbation&amp;rsquo;s effect isn&amp;rsquo;t always to create something novel, but often to change the balance of what&amp;rsquo;s already there. This is a critical concept for understanding drug resistance, where a therapy might simply select for a pre-existing resistant subclone rather than inducing a new program from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-this-informs-my-predictive-modeling-roadmap&#34;&gt;How This Informs My Predictive Modeling Roadmap&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper is not just another publication; it is the technical and philosophical blueprint for my entire research program. My mission is to build causal, predictive models of tissues, and Perturb-seq is the engine that generates the necessary data to make that possible. My focus on youth leukemia chemoresistance and solid tumor immunology hinges on understanding how cancer cells rewire their networks to survive therapy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the Perturb-seq framework, I can move beyond merely correlating gene expression with a resistant phenotype. I can now systematically knock out transcription factors, signaling molecules, or metabolic enzymes in a patient-derived model and directly observe which pathways are causally required for survival. This provides the raw, causal data needed to build a digital twin that doesn&amp;rsquo;t just describe the resistant state, but can &lt;em&gt;predict&lt;/em&gt; which nodes to target to reverse it. This paper provides the practical embodiment of my &amp;ldquo;Causality over Correlation&amp;rdquo; philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-horizon-my-next-move-and-the-fields-next-challenge&#34;&gt;The Horizon: My Next Move and the Field&amp;rsquo;s Next Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My Next Computational Step:&lt;/strong&gt; The linear model in MIMOSCA was a brilliant and necessary starting point, but biology is rarely linear. My immediate goal is to build on this foundation by developing non-linear models, likely leveraging graph neural networks or variational autoencoders, to capture more complex, synergistic relationships between perturbed genes. The ultimate objective is to build a model that can predict the transcriptional outcome of a &lt;em&gt;combination&lt;/em&gt; of perturbations it has never seen before, moving from inference to true out-of-sample prediction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Experiment for the Field:&lt;/strong&gt; The next frontier is to take this technology from 2D cell culture into more complex, in-vivo like systems. A critical experiment would be to combine Perturb-seq with co-culture organoid models or even direct in-vivo delivery in mouse models of leukemia. Imagine perturbing every known kinase in leukemia cells and then observing how those perturbations causally alter not only the cancer cell&amp;rsquo;s transcriptome but also its communication with the surrounding bone marrow stroma. That is how we will begin to map the networks that drive therapeutic resistance in a truly relevant biological context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-necessary-word-of-caution&#34;&gt;A Necessary Word of Caution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this work is foundational, it&amp;rsquo;s important to view this 2016 paper through a modern lens. The reliance on gene knockout is a blunt instrument; we now have access to CRISPR interference (CRISPRi) and activation (CRISPRa) for more subtle modulation. The computational model also has to contend with imperfect guide capture and variable knockout efficiency, requiring statistical inference to decide which cells were &amp;ldquo;truly&amp;rdquo; perturbed. This introduces a potential source of modeling noise. Finally, the scale, while groundbreaking for its time, is now more routine. The core challenge they identified—deconvolving combinatorial perturbations—remains the key bottleneck, as the experimental possibility space grows exponentially. Their work laid the foundation, but scaling the analysis to true combinatorial complexity is still the grand challenge for the field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reference: &lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2016.11.038&#34;&gt;Perturb-Seq: Dissecting Molecular Circuits with Scalable Single-Cell RNA Profiling of Pooled Genetic Screens&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
