<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Perturb-seq | Qingzhou Zhang</title>
    <link>https://zqzneptune.github.io/tags/perturb-seq/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://zqzneptune.github.io/tags/perturb-seq/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Perturb-seq</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>©2014-2025 Qingzhou Zhang (CC) BY-NC-SA 4.0. All thoughts and opinions here are my own.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://zqzneptune.github.io/images/icon_huf504e8a2f7c5cf9e43cec507892894a0_49847_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Perturb-seq</title>
      <link>https://zqzneptune.github.io/tags/perturb-seq/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>CROP-seq: Linking CRISPR&#39;s &#39;Cut&#39; to the Transcriptome&#39;s &#39;Consequence&#39;</title>
      <link>https://zqzneptune.github.io/post/2021-02-04_cropseqinit/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zqzneptune.github.io/post/2021-02-04_cropseqinit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-bottom-line-up-front&#34;&gt;The Bottom Line Up Front&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this foundational 2017 Nature Methods paper, Datlinger and colleagues introduce CROP-seq (CRISPR Droplet Sequencing), a technology that elegantly solves a major bottleneck in functional genomics. They engineered a lentiviral vector to make guide RNAs (gRNAs) directly detectable in droplet-based single-cell RNA-sequencing workflows. This masterstroke created a scalable method to link a specific genetic knockout to its complete, cell-wide transcriptional response, all within a single, pooled experiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bridging-the-chasm-between-what-if-and-what-is&#34;&gt;Bridging the Chasm Between &amp;lsquo;What If&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;What Is&amp;rsquo;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before methods like CROP-seq, the world of CRISPR screening was fundamentally divided. On one side, you had pooled screens. These were fantastic for scale—you could test thousands of gene knockouts in one flask—but the readouts were crude. You could measure which perturbations made cells live or die, or maybe turn a single reporter gene on or off. You knew &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; a gene was important, but the rich biology of &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; remained a black box.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other side were arrayed screens. Here, each perturbation was done in its own well, allowing for deep, high-content readouts like whole-transcriptome sequencing. This gave you the &amp;lsquo;why&amp;rsquo;, but at a tremendous cost in time, labor, and resources. The scale was pitiful. The central challenge was clear: how do you get the best of both worlds? How can we perform thousands of &amp;ldquo;what if&amp;rdquo; experiments (the perturbations) and simultaneously measure &amp;ldquo;what is&amp;rdquo; (the deep, transcriptomic state) for every single one?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-vector-is-the-message&#34;&gt;The Vector is the Message&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The genius of CROP-seq lies in a clever piece of molecular engineering that enables a massive computational payoff. Standard gRNAs are transcribed by RNA Polymerase III and lack the poly-A tail necessary for capture in most scRNA-seq protocols. The authors re-engineered the lentiviral vector, placing the entire gRNA expression cassette inside the 3&amp;rsquo; Long Terminal Repeat (LTR). During viral integration, this LTR is duplicated, resulting in a gRNA that is not only transcribed by Pol III to guide Cas9, but is &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; embedded within a polyadenylated Pol II transcript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the key that unlocks the entire method. Now, when a single cell is encapsulated in a droplet with an oligo-dT-barcoded bead, the bead captures both the cell’s mRNA and the transcript containing the gRNA. The computational task then becomes beautifully direct: after sequencing, we can map the reads from each cell&amp;rsquo;s barcode, identify the specific gRNA sequence present, and confidently assign that cell’s entire transcriptome to a single, known perturbation. This transforms a messy pool of millions of cells into thousands of discrete, interpretable perturbation experiments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-self-calibrating-screen&#34;&gt;The Self-Calibrating Screen&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What really makes this approach powerful is how the rich readout redefines the experiment itself. The proof-of-concept screen of T-cell receptor (TCR) activation is a perfect example. Instead of just asking whether a knockout blocked activation in a binary sense, they used the transcriptomes of the non-targeting control cells to define a continuous &amp;ldquo;TCR activation signature.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They could then place every single cell, regardless of its perturbation, along this axis. This allowed them to quantify with high resolution exactly &lt;em&gt;how much&lt;/em&gt; a knockout of a key kinase like &lt;code&gt;LCK&lt;/code&gt; blunted the response compared to a knockout of a downstream adaptor. The experiment generates its own internal reference and its own complex, multi-gene phenotypic metric &lt;em&gt;de novo&lt;/em&gt;. It moves us from a simple on/off switch to a high-fidelity biological rheostat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;placing-this-work-in-my-universe&#34;&gt;Placing This Work in My Universe&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper isn&amp;rsquo;t just relevant to my research program; it&amp;rsquo;s a cornerstone technology. My goal is to build predictive, causal models of tissue function and dysfunction, and that simply cannot be done with correlational data alone. Technologies like CROP-seq are the engines that produce the causal data I need to build these digital twins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For my work in youth leukemia, this is transformative. Instead of just cataloging the genes that are differentially expressed in chemoresistant T-ALL cells, I can use a CROP-seq screen to systematically knock out 500 candidate transcription factors and signaling molecules. By treating the pool with chemotherapy, I can directly identify the perturbations that &lt;em&gt;cause&lt;/em&gt; a cell to adopt a drug-tolerant transcriptional state. This is the direct path to identifying actionable targets to overcome resistance. The same logic applies directly to my interests in the tumor microenvironment and immunotherapy resistance. This method is the bridge between a static cellular atlas and a dynamic, predictive model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-horizon-my-next-move-and-the-fields-next-challenge&#34;&gt;The Horizon: My Next Move and the Field&amp;rsquo;s Next Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work opened a door to a new type of functional genomics, and the path forward is clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My Next Computational Step:&lt;/strong&gt; The paper largely examines perturbations in steady states. The real frontier is dynamics. My immediate focus is on developing analytical frameworks that integrate CROP-seq data from multiple time points following a perturbation (like drug treatment). The goal is to move beyond simple differential expression and build dynamic gene regulatory network models that infer the &lt;em&gt;trajectory&lt;/em&gt; of cellular response. Can we predict not just the endpoint of drug resistance, but the path a cell takes to get there? This requires marrying causal inference from the knockouts with temporal modeling from the time-series data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Experiment for the Field:&lt;/strong&gt; The logical next step is to take these screens in vivo and layer on spatial context. The critical experiment is to deploy a CROP-seq screen in a patient-derived xenograft model of leukemia, then analyze the bone marrow using spatial transcriptomics. This would allow us to link a genetic perturbation within a cancer cell to its cell-intrinsic effects &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; its influence on the surrounding microenvironment. Imagine knocking out a secreted factor in a leukemia cell and watching how it reprograms the transcriptional state of nearby stromal and immune cells. That is the future of functional cancer biology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-necessary-word-of-caution&#34;&gt;A Necessary Word of Caution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a pioneering study, it&amp;rsquo;s important to view the work with a critical eye. First, the method&amp;rsquo;s efficiency depends on successfully capturing the gRNA transcript; if that fails, you get a transcriptome without a cause, which is a wasted cell and an expensive problem. Second, the transcriptional effects of single gene knockouts can be subtle, often requiring hundreds of cells per perturbation to achieve statistical power. This poses a challenge to the cost-effectiveness of true genome-wide screens. Finally, CRISPR knockout is a blunt instrument. It tells you the consequence of total gene ablation, but not the more nuanced effects of graded knockdown or disruptions to specific protein functions, which will require the next generation of perturbation tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From What to Why: How Perturb-seq Rewrote the Rules of Functional Genomics</title>
      <link>https://zqzneptune.github.io/post/2021-02-03_perturbseqinit/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zqzneptune.github.io/post/2021-02-03_perturbseqinit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-core-finding-in-a-nutshell&#34;&gt;The Core Finding in a Nutshell&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m taking a look back at the foundational 2016 paper from the Regev and Friedman labs that introduced Perturb-seq. At its core, they developed a method that welds a pooled CRISPR screen to single-cell RNA sequencing. For the first time, this allowed them to systematically knock out genes and read out the full downstream transcriptional consequences in thousands of individual cells at once, in a single experiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-problem-a-chasm-between-scale-and-depth&#34;&gt;The Problem: A Chasm Between Scale and Depth&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before this work, functional genomics was a frustrating trade-off. We could either go big with pooled screens that measured simple, one-dimensional outputs like cell survival, or go deep with low-throughput, one-gene-at-a-time transcriptomics. There was simply no way to causally link hundreds of genetic perturbations to high-dimensional phenotypes at scale. How do you build a causal map of a cell&amp;rsquo;s regulatory network if you can only see one intersection at a time? This paper provided the first practical roadmap to bridge that chasm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;their-analytical-engine-a-linear-model-with-biological-awareness&#34;&gt;Their Analytical Engine: A Linear Model with Biological Awareness&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The elegance of Perturb-seq isn&amp;rsquo;t just in the wet lab design. Computationally, they built a framework called MIMOSCA (Multi-Input-Multi-Output-Single-Cell-Analysis). At its heart, it&amp;rsquo;s a regularized linear model that attributes changes in each gene&amp;rsquo;s expression to the presence of a specific sgRNA. The real genius, however, is how they layered in covariates. The model doesn&amp;rsquo;t just capture the perturbation&amp;rsquo;s effect; it systematically models and subtracts the confounding effects of technical noise (like sequencing depth per cell) and, most importantly, pre-existing biological heterogeneity (like cell cycle or differentiation state). This layered approach allows them to isolate the true, direct impact of the gene knockout from other sources of variation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-result-that-demands-attention&#34;&gt;The Result That Demands Attention&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most profound insight for me was their ability to disentangle direct transcriptional regulation from shifts in cell state proportions. When they first modeled the data from dendritic cells, the inferred regulatory network was a bit blurry (Fig 3A). The &amp;lsquo;aha!&amp;rsquo; moment came after they accounted for cell state. They realized that a transcription factor knockout might not create an entirely &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; cellular program, but rather push cells from, say, a &amp;ldquo;pro-inflammatory&amp;rdquo; state to an &amp;ldquo;antiviral&amp;rdquo; state—both of which already exist in the unperturbed population. After computationally correcting for this cell state shifting, the direct regulatory links became razor-sharp (Fig 3E). This is a fundamental lesson: a perturbation&amp;rsquo;s effect isn&amp;rsquo;t always to create something novel, but often to change the balance of what&amp;rsquo;s already there. This is a critical concept for understanding drug resistance, where a therapy might simply select for a pre-existing resistant subclone rather than inducing a new program from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-this-informs-my-predictive-modeling-roadmap&#34;&gt;How This Informs My Predictive Modeling Roadmap&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper is not just another publication; it is the technical and philosophical blueprint for my entire research program. My mission is to build causal, predictive models of tissues, and Perturb-seq is the engine that generates the necessary data to make that possible. My focus on youth leukemia chemoresistance and solid tumor immunology hinges on understanding how cancer cells rewire their networks to survive therapy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the Perturb-seq framework, I can move beyond merely correlating gene expression with a resistant phenotype. I can now systematically knock out transcription factors, signaling molecules, or metabolic enzymes in a patient-derived model and directly observe which pathways are causally required for survival. This provides the raw, causal data needed to build a digital twin that doesn&amp;rsquo;t just describe the resistant state, but can &lt;em&gt;predict&lt;/em&gt; which nodes to target to reverse it. This paper provides the practical embodiment of my &amp;ldquo;Causality over Correlation&amp;rdquo; philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-horizon-my-next-move-and-the-fields-next-challenge&#34;&gt;The Horizon: My Next Move and the Field&amp;rsquo;s Next Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My Next Computational Step:&lt;/strong&gt; The linear model in MIMOSCA was a brilliant and necessary starting point, but biology is rarely linear. My immediate goal is to build on this foundation by developing non-linear models, likely leveraging graph neural networks or variational autoencoders, to capture more complex, synergistic relationships between perturbed genes. The ultimate objective is to build a model that can predict the transcriptional outcome of a &lt;em&gt;combination&lt;/em&gt; of perturbations it has never seen before, moving from inference to true out-of-sample prediction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Experiment for the Field:&lt;/strong&gt; The next frontier is to take this technology from 2D cell culture into more complex, in-vivo like systems. A critical experiment would be to combine Perturb-seq with co-culture organoid models or even direct in-vivo delivery in mouse models of leukemia. Imagine perturbing every known kinase in leukemia cells and then observing how those perturbations causally alter not only the cancer cell&amp;rsquo;s transcriptome but also its communication with the surrounding bone marrow stroma. That is how we will begin to map the networks that drive therapeutic resistance in a truly relevant biological context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-necessary-word-of-caution&#34;&gt;A Necessary Word of Caution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this work is foundational, it&amp;rsquo;s important to view this 2016 paper through a modern lens. The reliance on gene knockout is a blunt instrument; we now have access to CRISPR interference (CRISPRi) and activation (CRISPRa) for more subtle modulation. The computational model also has to contend with imperfect guide capture and variable knockout efficiency, requiring statistical inference to decide which cells were &amp;ldquo;truly&amp;rdquo; perturbed. This introduces a potential source of modeling noise. Finally, the scale, while groundbreaking for its time, is now more routine. The core challenge they identified—deconvolving combinatorial perturbations—remains the key bottleneck, as the experimental possibility space grows exponentially. Their work laid the foundation, but scaling the analysis to true combinatorial complexity is still the grand challenge for the field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reference: &lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2016.11.038&#34;&gt;Perturb-Seq: Dissecting Molecular Circuits with Scalable Single-Cell RNA Profiling of Pooled Genetic Screens&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
